<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Go[ds] vvonderfull mercies in preseruing one aliue, which hanged fiue dayes, who was falsely accused.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842267</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842267</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6908</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6908)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 754:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Go[ds] vvonderfull mercies in preseruing one aliue, which hanged fiue dayes, who was falsely accused.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Allde dwelling on Lumbard-hill, [..,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Year of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>One aliue, which hanged fiue dayes = John Johnson, of Antwerp.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (-A, blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed, affecting title and imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, John, --  of Antwerp.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6908:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:6908:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <p>A True relation of Go<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvonderfull mercies, in preſeruing one aliue, which hanged fiue dayes, who was falſely accuſed.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edw: Allde.</hi> dwelling on <hi>Lambard-hill,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6908:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:6908:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->
            <head>A True Relation, of a moſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſtrange accident which hapned on a young man borne at <hi>Dort</hi> a towne in <hi>Holland:</hi> who trauailing betweene <hi>Franckfort</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> was falſely accuſed for a robbery, and executed for the ſame at a Towne called <hi>Bon,</hi> where he hanged fiue dayes, &amp; was by God mightily preſerued, to the great aſtoniſhment of all the beholders.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>N the towne of <hi>Dort</hi>
               </hi> vpon the long reede Banke (neere the ſigne of the three Pidgions) there dwelled a man whoſe name was <hi>Iohn Peterſon,</hi> borne in the Citie of <hi>Antwerp:</hi> who maried with a young woman, borne at <hi>Dort</hi> aforeſaid: This <hi>Iohn Peterſon</hi> with his wife liued many yeares together, he being a waterman, who v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ferry paſſengers from <hi>Dort</hi> to <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> and his wife vſed the trade of dreſſing of Flax: theſe two hauing had diuers children, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God that all dyed ſauing two Sonnes,
<pb facs="tcp:6908:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->whoſe names were, the one Nicholas <hi>Iohnſon</hi> who now dwelleth at the <hi>Brill,</hi> the other <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> (for often they take their ſurnames of their Fathers Chriſten name) of which <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> we are heereafter to intreat: whoſe Parents dyed in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1600.</hi> being very poore.</p>
            <p>This Iohn <hi>Peterſon</hi> being deceaſed, hauing a brother yet dwelling in the Citie of <hi>Antwerp</hi> who vnderſtanding of the death of his brother ſent to <hi>Dort</hi> for <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> the youngeſt ſon of his brother deceaſed (being a pretty youth) who thought it fitter to keepe one of his owne kinſmen, then the ſonne of any ſtranger: When this youth came to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> his Vncle gaue him very kinde welcome, being ioyfull to ſee him, for he had neuer ſeene him before that time. Now it pleaſed his Vncle to imploy this <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> about his affaires, who vſed ſuch diligence in all things he went about, that he procured ſuch loue of his Vncle, as if he had bene his deare childe, he could neuer haue reſpected him with more regard: and the rather, for that he gaue his minde to all vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; godly exerciſes: Inſomuch, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the young man did, it was moſt pleaſing to his Vncle, as alſo to moſt who knew him: He was many times aſſailed by Ieſuits (and others of that religion) to conuert him from the true religion which he then profeſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:6908:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->but he continuing conſtant, by no meanes would yeild vnto them: which being bruited in the Citie, he was of all the godly generally well reſpected.</p>
            <p>To come to the matter: his Vncle being a man of great trading in marchandize, had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion (with diuers other marchants) to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile to <hi>Francfort</hi> Mart (for he vſed much to go thither) and thought it fit to take his kinſman <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> along with him, to acquaint him in thoſe partes, that he might the better afterwards haue knowledge in his buſines: &amp; his Vncle delighted greatly in his company, by reaſon he was giuen to much honeſt mirth, for which all that knew him did exceedingly affect him, and called him the Hollander, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding often of him, if all Hollanders were ſo pleaſant as himſelfe was paſſing on the way? After their long iourney, they came to <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> euery man taking his leaue of other, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to goe about their affaires: And after ſome few daies of their continuance in <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> there came a Letter to this <hi>Iohn Iohnſons</hi> Vncle (from <hi>Antwerp</hi>) to certifye him of buſines of great import, which was ſpeedily to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched at home: whervpon his Vncle hauing as yet effected little buſines, did thinke it moſt conuenient to ſend the ſaid <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twerp</hi> (knowing his ſufficient care in any of his imployments) whilſt he himſelfe ſtayed till the
<pb facs="tcp:6908:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->end of the Mart. Now hauing commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Vncle to depart for <hi>Antwerp,</hi> hee tooke his leaue, and ſet forward on his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney without any feare, for he had little to looſe, and taking his iourneys to the ſame Townes and Innes, where before he with his Vncle &amp; other Marchants had lyen: At length he came to <hi>Bon,</hi> to the ſame Inne where he before had lodged, which was neere the market-place, at the ſigne of the Swan, without ſuſpect of any danger: where alſo lodged diuers Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, with whome this <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> that night ſupped, hauing had very good fare: and paſſing the time away with pleaſant diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, vntill it grew towards bed-time: and being ſhewed their chambers, the young-man deſired the Hoſt that he would call him vp ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry early, who promiſing ſo to doe, departed: This Hoſt hauing eſpied one of the other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants to haue a Budget, wherein was good ſtore of money, (who lodged in the ſame Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where the young man lodged) thought with himſelfe how he might get this Bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, and to liue vnſuſpected: at laſt he deuiſed with himſelfe, that hauing the mony, he would work ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ningly that none ſhould be ſuſpected but the young man: The Hoſt in the night came ſtealing into their chamber, there taking away the Marchants Budget with money, and the young mans Wallet, wherein was
<pb facs="tcp:6908:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->ſome foule linnen, and ſhooes, and ſuch like. When this Hoſt had opened the Marchants Budget, and taken out the mony, he found al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the ſame a Seale Ring &amp; an Obligation, which Obligation and Seale-ring, the Hoſt tooke out, and with a ſiluer Tonne of his owne, whereon the Hoſts marke was gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and which his gueſts did drinke in the night before at Supper, hee put theſe three in the young mans wallet, and tyed it vp as it was afore, and entring the Chamber againe laid the wallet in the place from whence he tooke it.</p>
            <p>In the morning the Hoſt (according to his promiſe) calles vp the young man, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently riſing, made him ready, paid his recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, tooke his leaue, and went his way on his iourney, hauing the Marchants King and Obligation, with the Hoſts ſiluer Tonne, tyed vp in his wallet, vnknowne vnto him: ſo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayling on without any miſtruſt, it fortuned that the Marchant aryſing, and miſſing his Budget with his money, preſently called out, ſaying he was robd: and being exceedingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, and in a great fury, the Hoſt (as if hee had not knowne any thing) come ſpeedily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, demaunding the occaſion of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To whome hee replyed that his Bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get with his money was ſtolne away from him: The Hoſt anſwering, that if hee had loft any
<pb facs="tcp:6908:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->thing, there was none could haue it but the youth who lodged that night in the Chamber, and was ſo ſodainely gone away in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Therefore let vs with all ſpeede take horſe, &amp; we ſhall ſurely ouertake him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, with all haſte that might be, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, with the treacherous hoaſt, tooke their Horſes, and in very ſhort time they ouertooke this <hi>Iohn Iohnſon:</hi> The Hoaſt ſpeaking very furiouſly vnto him, charged him of Fellony, ſaying, thou haſt robbed this Marchant (who lay this night in the ſame Chamber where thy ſelfe didſt lodge) of all his money: The modeſt young man, at the firſt being greatly affrighted ſtood amazed, knowing himſelfe without fault, anſwered: Truly I am as cleer from ſuch offence, as any perſon in the world: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the Hoſt was marueylous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate to haue the young mans wallet ſearcht, which being opened, there appeared to their fight, the Hoſts ſiluer Tonne, with the Marchants Obligation and ſeale King: which when the Marchant eſpied, he thought verily that none had his money but he: The young man when he ſaw theſe things pulled out of his Mallet, almoſt dyed with griefe, excuſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he neuer knew how they came into his Wallet: but the Boaſt vowed that hee ſhould be hanged if it ſhould coſt him an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth pound: So cauſing the youth to returne
<pb facs="tcp:6908:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->backe againe to <hi>Bon,</hi> they brought him before the Magiſtrates, who after his examination, he ſtill denying the fact, was committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, put vpon the Racke, and grieuouſly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: the youth feeling this miſerable paine, cryed to God for ayde, and voluntarily confeſt that he had done the deed, although indeed he did it not: Afterward, being brought to the publike place of tryall, he was there ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to be hanged for that oftence: But when he perceaued that he muſt needs die the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death, he lamenting all his ſinfull life paſt, which he had committed againſt the Maieſtie of Almighty God, he hoped to be ſaued in the faith he had in Ieſus Chriſt: So being led to the place of execution, in the preſence of all the beholders, ſaid: I am here come to ſuffer death in this place, and now in preſence of you all, I take God to be my witnes (&amp; therewith wept moſt bitterly) that I neuer knew of the ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling either of the Marchants money, neither of the Hoaſts ſiluer Tonne, nor can any way deuiſe by what meanes they ſhould come into my Mallet: and in reſpect I am cleere of this fact for which I am heere condemned to die, I doe beſeech Almightie God that it will pleaſe him through his great power, to ſhew ſome mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle on me, whereby the truth may be known; and that all men may perceane that I ſuffered innocently: the people grieued much to heare
<pb facs="tcp:6908:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->him inuocate the name of God in that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, prayed alſo with him and lamented his timeles death, if he were as he ſaide without fault: ſo hauing ended his prayers, he was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned off the Ladder and hanged: but the Lord God hauing heard his prayers, and knowing his innocencie, did moſt miraculouſly preſerue him, as heereafter you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>His Uncle hauing ended all his buſines at <hi>Francfort,</hi> in the company of diuers other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, tooke their iournies homewards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and according to their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted manner they tooke their Inne (where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were accuſtomed) at the Signe of the Swan in the Towne of <hi>Bon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the morning following, when theſe Marchants intended to depart from thence, The hoaſt being amongſt them, tolde them that there was a young man, which was in their company the laſt time that they lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged there, who had robbed him of a ſiluer Tonne which they vſed to drinke in, and a Marchant (which lodged in the houſe) of a great ſumme of money: for which offence, the young man was apprehended, and afterwards confeſt the fact, and then adiudged to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, which is now fiue daies ſince he was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and ſtill hangeth on the gallowes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the gates.</p>
            <p>The young mans Vncle being ſtroken into
<pb facs="tcp:6908:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->wonderful admiration at this ſpeech, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Hoſt what manner a fellow he was which committed the robbery? he being well aſſured that his kinſman would not commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch abuſe: but by the Hoaſts deſcription, in all things it was his kinſman: wherevpon, becauſe he would be certaine whether it was he or no, he earneſtly requeſted the other Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants which were with him, to take ſo much paines, as to goe with him to ſee him, for hee could hardly yet belieue it to be him.</p>
            <p>And comming to the place where the young man hanged, ſo ſoone as he came neere him, he eſpied him to be his kinſman, at the ſight wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he ſodainely fell downe in a ſwound: but the Marchants helping him vp, comforted him with all their helpes. Preſently, the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (there hanging) ſpake to his Vncle in this manner following.</p>
            <p>O my louing and moſt deere Vncle, although I heere hang moſt ſhamefully, yet am I not dead, for it hath pleaſed Almighty God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me, by placing a ſtoole vnder my feete, which to you is not perceaued, vpon the which I ſtand, And the Angell of the Lord, from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hath fed me heere fiue dayes: I beſeech you take the paines, to returne to the Towne of <hi>Bon,</hi> and certifye the Maieſtrater there, in what manner you haue found me, and requeſt them to come with you, and I will let them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb facs="tcp:6908:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->that I am heere hanged without any offence: The Marchants hearing the young man ſpeaking in this manner, were much aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, and ſtraight-way departed from thence: and when they came before the Magiſtrates, they before them vpon their Oathes deliuered what the young man had related vnto them: whereat the Magiſtrates maruailed, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with the Marchants they went to the place where the young man did hang, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing al to be true which the Marchants had reported vnto them, they cauſed him to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently taken downe, who was then in perfect health, although he had hanged fiue dayes.</p>
            <p>But God, the defender of all that put their whole truſt in his mercies, ſeeing this young mans innocencie (to make his wondrous workes to ſeeme the more admirable, and to bring the truth to light) preſerued him all this time, without any perill or danger.</p>
            <p>Then the Magiſtrates (in the company of thoſe Marchants) hauing ſeene this miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous worke of the Lord, brought this <hi>Iohn Iohnſon</hi> into the Towne, where they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined this youth throughly of all doubts, who certifyed them of all the manner: firſt of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſuch an Inne, then how he requeſted his Hoſt to call him vp in the morning, then of his departing, and afterwards how the Hoſt with the Marchant came riding after him, and apprehended him: which when they perceaued,
<pb facs="tcp:6908:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->preſently they ſent for the Hoſt, to examine him vpon the perticulers, touching this young man: but when the Hoſt beheld the young man ſtill to be aliue, the Hoſt preſently confeſſed the deed, &amp; how hee himſelfe had wrongfully accuſed that youth of thoſe fellonies which he himſelfe had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted. When theſe Magiſtrats heard all the truth of this buſines, they praiſed God for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing this young man, and brigning to light the wretched offender: And ſo ſentence was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced vpon this Hoſt, that he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed to priſon, and the next day to be bound to a Stake neere the place where the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was hanged, and there to be burnt: which was accordingly performed. And likewiſe it was ordered by thoſe Iudges that the young man ſhould poſſeſſe to his own vſe, the ſomme of three thouſand Guilders, of the Hoſts money, in recompence of the iniurie was done vnto him.</p>
            <p>After this execution was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iniſhed, the young man, with his Uncle, &amp; the other Marchants, taking their leaues of the Magiſtrates, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards <hi>Antwerp</hi> where now this <hi>Iohn Johnſon,</hi> with his Uncle <hi>Gerard Atthonyſon,</hi> doe at this day remaine, neere a place called the Meere, or water. Whoſoeuer doe repaire to that place, may be an eye-witnes, &amp; ſee the party who was executed as before is declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Magiſtrates of <hi>Bon,</hi> cauſed this to be Printed, to ſet forth the mighty power and glorie of God, as themſelues were witneſſes thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
